Guide to the Picture File, 1600s-1979 and undated, bulk 1814-1950
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Picture File 1600s-1979 and undated, bulk 1814-1950
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
10.5 Linear Feet 6016 Items
The Picture File was created by the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a vertical file from the 1950s to the 1980s. Images were separated from manuscript collections as well as added individually from other sources.
The Picture File is a large and diverse collection of visual materials ranging from the 17th through the 20th centuries. The bulk of the images in the collection date from the early 1800s through the 1950s. Formats represented include black and white photographic prints; cartes de visite, cabinet cards and other albumen prints; tintypes and daguerreotypes; engravings and lithographs; political cartoons; watercolors; sketches; postcards; stereographs; souvenir albums; leaflets; and small broadsides. Organized into four main series: Subjects, Geographic, Socialist Party, and People. The images offer representations of the landscape, culture, and history of most of the southern United States, especially Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Maryland, North and South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia. Many images of France, Italy, Germany, Japan, China, and some African countries can also be found; a large number of other countries and geographic locations are represented by only a few images. Many political figures and notable personages are portrayed; there are especially significant numbers of images of Eugene Debs, Socialist Party leader, and members of the Duke family of Durham, N.C. The history of that same city is also well-represented, in addition to other Southern cities and towns, including Raleigh N.C. Civil War images are abundant, offering views of battles and scenes of devastation both rural and urban. Other conflicts are also depicted, including the American Revolutionary War, Spanish-American War, and there are some images from both World Wars. A significant group of items in the People Series pertains to African Americans, ranging from studio portraits to caricatures of individuals and groups of individuals; a smaller group of images features depictions of Native Americans. Finally, the Picture File is home to collections of many engravings and lithographs produced by the 19th century American companies Currier and Ives, L. Prang and Co., and Kurz and Allison; many of them commemorate military leaders or events.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Picture File was created by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a vertical file from about 1950 to 1989.
Collection Overview
The Picture File is a large and diverse collection of visual materials ranging from the 17th through the 20th centuries. The bulk of the images in the collection date from the early 1800s through the 1950s. Formats represented include black and white photographic prints; cartes de visite, cabinet cards and other albumen prints; tintypes and daguerreotypes; engravings and lithographs; political cartoons; watercolors; sketches; postcards; stereographs; souvenir albums; leaflets; and small broadsides. Organized into four main series: Subjects, Geographic, Socialist Party, and People. The images offer representations of the landscape, culture, and history of most of the southern United States, especially Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Maryland, North and South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia. Many images of France, Italy, Germany, Japan, China, and some African countries can also be found; a large number of other countries and geographic locations are represented by only a few images. Many political figures and notable personages are portrayed; there are especially significant numbers of images of Eugene Debs, Socialist Party leader, and members of the Duke family of Durham, N.C. The history of that same city is also well-represented, in addition to other Southern cities and towns, including Raleigh N.C. Civil War images are abundant, offering views of battles and scenes of devastation both rural and urban. Other conflicts are also depicted, including the American Revolutionary War, Spanish-American War, and there are some images from both World Wars. A significant group of items in the People Series pertains to African Americans, ranging from studio portraits to caricatures of individuals and groups of individuals; a smaller group of images features depictions of Native Americans. Finally, the Picture File is home to collections of many engravings and lithographs produced by the 19th century American companies Currier and Ives, L. Prang and Co., and Kurz and Allison; many of them commemorate military leaders or events.
The great majority of images in the the relatively small Subjects Series (about 120 items) depict scenes from the Revolutionary, Civil, Spanish-American, and World Wars, but other images relate to such diverse subjects as architecture, automobiles, horses, ships, and politics. This series includes a large collection of Currier and Ives prints and American political cartoons.
The much larger Geographic Series contains visual representations of many regions in the United States, with the largest concentration belonging to the Southern states. Almost half the series is comprised of images depicting Civil War scenes, during and after the war, and are chiefly engravings of battles or photographs of urban devastation. There are very few images of individual soldiers; however, there are reunion group photographs and portraits of Civil War military leaders (many more can be found in the People Series). A few images were taken by noted photographer Alexander Gardner. Other photographs and postcards, many from the 19th century, depict factories, buildings and monuments, street scenes in cities, social events, and rural landscapes. Durham, N.C. is especially well-represented, and many of the locations relate to the Duke family. Souvenir albums and postcards of Florida, New Orleans, Niagara Falls, and other tourist destinations appear frequently. Other geographical locations in this series include many European countries and Asian countries. Particularly of interest are early 20th century images of conflicts in Europe, Japan and China.
The images in the Socialist Party Records Series provide a rich additional resource to the papers of the Socialist Party America, also held by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Subdivided into groupings entitled General, Geographic, Labor, and People, the series documents in visual form the history of the party and its membership, chiefly from the early 1900s to the 1970s, with emphasis on the decades from the 1920s through the 1940s. Images include portraits of leading individuals such as Eugene V. Debs, and photographs taken at many conventions and meetings throughout the U.S. Other scenes depicted include strikes, protests, and elections.
The People Series is the largest series, comprising nearly two-thirds of the collection. Portraits of well-known military, political, literary, religious, and historical figures from Western society are depicted chiefly through engravings, though there are many photographs of modern figures; all are arranged in alphabetical order. Confederate Civil War military figures are well represented. Subdivisions house images of Native Americans and African Americans, chiefly in photographs and postcards; the older and outdated series titles, Negroes and Indians, have been retained, but cross references have been provided using modern terms Native Americans and African Americans.
Collection Arrangement Note:
To allow for better housing, negatives, stereographs, and cased images such as daguerreotypes have been separated into their own series.
Oversize materials separated from the main collection at processing are housed in flat oversize boxes and appear listed in subseries at the end of each of the main series to which they belong. Cross-references to all separated materials are provided at the original folder locations from which items have been removed. Another large group of oversize materials separated earlier in the collection's history is listed in a separate series at the end of this finding aid; these items are housed in large oversize boxes belonging to the Special Collections Library's on-site oversize box run, and the largest are housed in the library's oversize cabinets.
To facilitate access to all of the images and to undertake the most comprehensive search for materials, researchers may wish to contact the Research Services staff before using this collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
African Americans -- Portraits
Native Americans -- Portraits
Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926
Labor leaders -- United States -- Portraits
Socialism -- United States -- History -- Pictorial works
Southern States -- Pictorial works
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Pictorial works
United States -- History -- Revolutionary War -- Pictorial works
Socialist Party, USA -- Pictorial works
Currier and Ives
L. Prang and Co
Kurz and Allison
North Carolina -- History -- Pictorial works
Virginia -- History -- Pictorial works
South Carolina -- History -- Pictorial works
Georgia -- History -- Pictorial works
Florida -- History -- Pictorial works
Alabama -- History -- Pictorial works
Kentucky -- History -- Pictorial works
Tennessee -- History -- Pictorial works
United States -- History -- Pictorial works
Durham, N.C.--History -- Pictorial works
United States -- Politics and government -- Pictorial works
Duke family
Duke University -- History -- Pictorial works
Raleigh, N.C.--History -- Pictorial works
France -- History -- Pictorial works
Italy -- History -- Pictorial works
Germany -- History -- Pictorial works
Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Pictorial works
Japan -- History -- Pictorial works
Italy -- History -- Pictorial works
Postcards
Stereographs
Engravings
Lithographs
Albumen prints
Black and white photographs
Political cartoons
Daguerreotypes
Tintypes
Watercolors (drawings).
Souvenir albums
Contents of Collection
- Subjects Series, 1814-1946, circa 1940s and undated, (2 boxes)
  Items relating to a variety of subjects, including architecture, automobiles, fashion, political cartoons, and military conflicts, particularly the American Civil War but also the Revolutionary, Spanish-American, and World Wars. The Civil War images, which include several photographs by noted photographer Alexander Gardner, make up more than half of the Subjects Series; most of the items are engravings of battle scenes and photographs of battlefields and forts. The entire series is primarily comprised of engravings and photographs, though there are lithograph, paper prints, a souvenir album, photostats and tintypes as well. In addition, some materials were separated from the main collection to allow for better housing; these include negatives, stereographs, and oversized materials. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Architecture, Domestic, 1800s and undated
    - Farmhouse (unidentified), undated, (black-and-white photograph) (Box 1, Folder M1)
    - "Progress," undated, (4 photographs of engravings) (Folder M2)
      Transferred from the David E. Evans Papers.
      These pictures bear no formal title. They show the development of a farm from the time it was settled until it became a prosperous establishment.
    - Town house (unidentified) with four people, 1800s, (card photograph) (Folder M3)
  - Architecture-Libraries-Europe, undated
    - Stechert portfolio of twelve engravings of famous European libraries, undated, (6 engravings) (Box 1, Folder M4.1)
      Includes index of engravings.
    - Stechert portfolio of twelve engravings of famous European libraries, undated, (6 engravings) (Folder M4.2)
  - Art, undated
    - "Intercepted Despatches," undated, (engraving) (Box 1, Folder M5)
    - "Landscape: The 'Weierhaus,' near Nuremberg," undated, (black-and-white illustration) (Folder M5a)
      Photo of Durer original in the British Museum.
    - Study for engraving of "The Prodigal Son," undated, (black-and-white illustration) (Folder M5b)
    - "The Rhinoceros," undated, (black-and-white illustration) (Folder M5c)
    - Madonna and an unidentified painting, undated, (2 card photographs) (Folder M6)
  - Automobiles, 1919-1922
    - American automobiles, 1919-1922, (5 black-and-white photographs) (Box 1, Folder M7.1)
      Individual photos of Cadillac, Chevrolet, and Ford automobiles.
      Transferred from the Duke Undergraduate Library.
    - American automobiles, 1919-1922, (4 black-and-white photographs) (Folder M7.2)
  - Political Cartoons, undated
    - "An Unpublished Cartoon of Reconstruction Days in South Carolina - An Amateur Artist's Conception of Scott's Administration (1868-1872)," undated, (black-and-white photograph) (Box 1, Folder M8)
    - "It's no Use a Knocking at the Doors," undated, (card photograph) (Folder M9)
  - Costumes, 1909
    - Ku Klux Costumes, [1868], 1909, (card photograph) (Box 1, Folder M10)
      Drawing from a photograph made in 1868 by Federal soldiers who captured the costumes after a Ku Klux Klan parade.
  - Fashion, 1800s, 1872 and undated
    - American bridal dress and veil (bride unidentified), undated, (card photograph) (Box 1, Folder M11)
    - Unidentified individuals, 1872 and 1800s, (12 card photographs) (Folder M12.1)
    - Unidentified individuals, 1800s, (7 card photographs) (Folder M12.2)
    - Unidentified individuals, 1800s, (card photograph) (Folder M12.3)
    - Unidentified individuals, undated, (2 tintypes) (Folder M12.4)
  - Horses, 1865 and undated
    - General Philip Henry Sheridan's horse (name unknown), undated, (card photograph) (Box 1, Folder M13)
    - "General Grant's Horse 'Jeff Davis,'" 1865, (stereograph)
      Removed to Stereographs Series.
  - Trucks, circa 1927
    - Dump Trucks by Corbitt, circa 1927, (3 black-and-white photographs) (Box 1, Folder M14)
      From the Frank C. Brown Papers, Duke Archives.
  - Revolutionary War, 1900s, 1902 and undated
    - "Battle of Bunker Hill," undated, (engraving) (Box 1, Folder M15)
      From Jones: Biographical Sketches of the Delegates from Georgia to the Continental Congress
    - Revolutionary war engravings, undated, (5 engravings) (Folder M16)
      - "Battle of Camden - Death of De Kalb," undated
      - "Battle of Cowpens...," undated
      - "Battle of Eutaw Springs," undated
      - "Battle of Eutaw Springs," undated
      - "Cornwallis Surrendering the British Standards at Yorktown," undated
      - "Female Patriotism - Mrs. Steele and Genl. Green," undated
        Missing. "Removed for Women's Exhibit 2/15/83."
    - Monument marking site of battle of Cooch's Bridge, 1900s, (card photograph) (Folder M17)
    - "Picture of Shot Gun Used in Battle of Guilford Court House...," 1902 Jan. 16, (card photograph)
      Removed to OV Folder 1, Box SM01, Oversize Subseries.
  - Ships, 1814-1934 and undated
    - "Confederate States Ram 'Arkansas'," undated, (2 photostats (Box 1, Folder M18)
      Includes duplicate copy of photostat image.
    - "Eyes of the Fleet Draw Eyes of the Chief," 1934 May 31, (black-and-white photograph) (Folder M19)
      Ship pictured is the U.S.S. Indianapolis. More detailed information provided on back of photograph.
    - The Maine, undated, (card photograph) (Folder M20)
    - The Minnesota, undated, (black-and-white photograph) (Folder M21)
    - "Peacock and L'Epervier," 1814 Apr. 29, (engraving) (Folder M22)
      Transferred from the Marmaduke Floyd Collection.
  - Spanish-American War, 1898 and undated
    - Spanish-American War stereographs, 1898, (4 stereographs) (Box 1)
      - Major Coe, 21st U.S. Infantry, Camp Tampa, Fla.
      - "A part of Gen. Miles' Porto Rican Army -- before embarking at Newport News, Va."
      - Troop C, Vol. Cavalry from Brooklyn, Camp Alger, Va.
      - Troop I, 6th U.S. Cavalry, Camp Tampa, Fla.
    - "Around the Camp Fire, Chickamauga, Ga., U.S.A.; 'Our Boys' at Santiago. A Rest by the Roadside," 1898 and undated, (2 stereographs)
  - U.S. Civilian Conservation Corps, 1900s
    - "Dining Hall, Joyce Kilmer C.C.C Camp No.148," 1900s, (black-and-white photograph) (Box 1, Folder M23)
  - Weddings, circa 1940s
    - Unidentified bride and groom, circa 1940s, (black-and-white photograph) (Box 1, Folder M24)
  - World War I, 1918
    - American and German prisoners of war reading Wilson's message to the Kaiser, 1918 Oct. 24, (black-and-white photograph) (Box 1, Folder M25)
  - World War II, 1944-1946
    - World War II news photographs, 1946 Jan. 16 and 22, (3 black-and-white photographs) (Box 1, Folder M26)
      Detailed information provided on backs of photographs.
      - "Italian Prisoners Go Home"
      - "Leaving U.S. for Italy"
      - "GI's Demonstrate in Paris"
    - Photographs taken in France, 1944-1945, (6 black-and-white photographs) (Folder M27)
      - "Bastille Day in France..."
      - "Battle in streets of Chartres"
      - "Dutch troops arrive in Normandy"
      - "First American cemetery in France..."
      - Photograph taken in an office
      - "Psychological warfare in action"
  - Civil War, 1862-1892 and undated
    - "Action Between the Kearsarge and Alabama. (Rescue of the crew of the Alabama by the Deerhound)," undated, (engraving) (Box 1, Folder M28)
    - "Action of the Gunboats at Memphis," undated, (engraving) (Folder M29)
      From the original painting by Chappel.
    - "Appearance of Fort Sumter on Sunday Afternoon August 23d 1863," undated, (lithograph)
      Removed to Oversize Subseries.
    - "Attack on Fredericksburgh - Dec. 1862," 1862 Dec. 13, (engraving) (Folder M30)
    - "Attack of the Rebels upon our Gun Boats in Galveston Harbor," undated, (engraving) (Folder M31)
    - "Attack Upon Roanoke Island - Landing of the Troops," undated, (engraving) (Folder M32)
    - "Attack at Rocky Face Ridge, Ga.," undated, (engraving) (Folder M33)
    - "Battle of Ball's Bluff, Va. - Rescuing the body of Brig. Gen. Baker," undated, (engraving) (Folder M34)
    - "Battle of Bull Run - July 1861 (Gen. Blenker's Brigade covering the retreat.)," undated, (engraving) (Folder M35)
    - "Battle of Chicamauga - Lt. Van Pelt Defending his Battery," undated, (engraving) (Folder M36)
    - "Battle of Lookout Mountain, Ga.," undated, (engraving) (Folder M37)
    - Battle of Lookout Mountain, "Ropers Rock Showing First Union Troops Scaling Cliffs - Nov 25th 1863," undated, (black-and-white photograph) (Folder M38)
      Given by Mrs. I. E. Gray, Durham, NC.
    - "Battle of Malvern Hill, Va. - U.S. Gun Boats on James River Covering the Retreat," undated, (engraving) (Folder M39)
    - "Battle of Murfreesboro - Capture of a Confederate Flag," undated, (engraving) (Folder M40)
    - "Battle of the Rams," undated, (engraving) (Folder M41)
    - "Battle of Rich Mountain," undated, (engraving) (Folder M42)
    - "Battle of Shiloh, Tenn. - Charge of General Grant," undated, (2 engravings) (Folder M43)
      Duplicate copy included.
    - "Battle at Wilson's Creek, Mo.," undated, (engraving) (Folder M44)
    - "Bird's Eye View of Confederate Prison Pen - at Salisbury, N.C. - Taken in 1864," undated, (black-and-white photograph) (Folder M45)
      Includes brief notes specifying different parts of the prison.
    - "Bombardment of Island no.10 - Gun and Mortar Boats on the Mississippi," undated, (engraving) (Folder M46)
    - "Bombardment of Port Royal, S.C. - Transport Fleet in the Distance," undated, (2 engravings) (Folder M47)
      Includes names of depicted ships and forts. Duplicate copy included.
    - "Capture of Fort Donelson, Tenn. - Charge of Gen. Smith's Division," undated, (engraving) (Box 2, Folder M48)
    - "Capture of New Orleans -- The Fleet Passing Forts on the Mississippi," undated, (engraving) (Folder M49)
      Includes names of depicted ships.
    - "Capture of the Works at Petersburg," undated, (engraving) (Folder M50)
    - "Castle Thunder, Richmond, Looking Up Carey Street," 1865 Apr. 7, A. Gardner, photographer, (card photograph) (Folder M51)
    - "Columbia After Sherman's Visit," undated, (6 black-and-white photographs) (Folder M52)
      May be 19th c. reproductions of card photographs.
      - "Catholic Convent, S.E. Corner Blanding and Main Street -- Where Tapp's Store is Now"
      - "Christ Episcopal Church, S.E. Corner of Blanding and Marion Streets"
      - "Freight Depot of S.C.R.R. - Later Rebuilt"
      - "Lutheran Church (Ebenezer)"
      - "Main Street from State House Grounds"
      - "Washington Street M.E. Church"
    - Confederate flags and seals, undated, (5 colored and uncolored paper prints (Folder M53)
      From the Chas E. Jones Papers scrapbook.
    - Confederate monument, Augusta, Ga., undated, (4 colored and uncolored paper prints (Folder M54)
      Affixed to a single scrapbook page.
    - "Design for Monument to Gen. E. Kirby Smith, Sewanee, Tenn.," undated, (3 uncolored paper prints (Folder M55)
    - "Experience of the 9th Mass. Battery at Gettysburg, Penn., July, 1863," undated, (card photograph) (Folder M56)
    - "First Naval Combat Between Iron Vessels," 1862 Mar. 9, (engraving) (Folder M57)
    - "Fort McAllister," 1865, (engraving) (Folder M58)
      Taken from The Story of the Great March. From The Diary of a Staff Officer, by Brevet Major George Wards Nichols, aide-de-camp to General Sherman, Harper and Bros., New York, 1865.
    - "Fort Pennsylvania, Head Quarters of the 113th Regt. N.Y.S.V. - Col. O. L. Morricee, Comm.," undated, (lithograph)
      Removed to Folder OV3, Box SM01, Oversize Subseries.
    - "Fort Sumter 'Repossessed' by the Union, Feb. 18, 1865," undated, (lithograph) (Folder M59)
    - [Gettysburg] "The Last Day at the Battle of Gettysburg," 1892, (stereograph)
    - [Gettysburg] "Notes on the Invasion of Maryland and Pennsylvania and The Battle of Gettysburg with Explanatory Map and Souvenir Album," circa 1888, (souvenir album) (Folder M60)
      Map missing; contains about 50 small images, seem to be ink drawings taken from postcards or photographs; some are reproductions of Paul Philippoteaux paintings. Handle with care; bindings fragile.
    - "Group of relics in Charleston, S.C., Arsenal...," undated, stereograph)
      Relics include Confederate torpedoes, shot, shell, and breach of the 600 lb. Blakely Gun.
    - "Landing of Troops on Roanoke Island -- Burnside Expedition," 1862, (engraving) (Folder M61)
    - Libbey Prison, Richmond, Va., 1865 Apr. 6, A. Gardner, photographer, (2 card photographs) (Folder M62)
      One stereograph removed to S6 in the Stereographs Series.
    - "Linn's Lookout Mountain Views," undated, (stereograph)
      One view of the stereograph is missing.
    - "Massachusetts Militia Passing Through Baltimore," [1862], (engraving)
      Removed to Folder OV4, Box SM01, Oversize Subseries.
    - Morris Island, S.C., 1863 July-Sept. Haas and Peale, photographers, (6 black-and-white photographs) (Folder M63.1)
      These photographs were made from glass-plate negatives contained in the Library of Congress.